I do these annually as I did last year
and here we are again to go over a list
of supplements that I reviewed across a
total of 62 studies. Last year I used a
dual criteria for assessing supplements.
So one the strength of the scientific
evidence and two the magnitude of the
effect. I'd like to do the same thing
here, but instead of giving a single
letter grade, it's better if we discuss
them independently. As a supplement can
have great evidence behind it, but have
very mild effects. Anyway, as a final
warning before we dive in, these
supplements are assessed based on
specific outcomes. So, if we end up
discussing like omega-3s for the heart,
that conclusion should be limited to
that outcome. So heart health and should
not be extended to other outcomes like I
don't know let's say bone health for
example. Okay as usual I'll link all my
dedicated video investigations popping
open the data and going over the
mechanisms and such for you in the
description if you want more information
on any particular supplement. But let's
get into these 15. Oh, and at the end
I'll tell you which ones that I'd
recommend focusing on. Not that this is
personalized advice, of course.
Bourberine for colon cancer. This was a
recent investigation that really blew me
away because the study was incredibly
compelling. Actually, it was two studies
based on a single randomized control
trial. Essentially, compared to placebo,
participants given bourberin had reduced
number and severity of colon adenomomas,
which are these abnormal growths. The
most mind-blowing part was that after
they stopped consuming bourbon, they
still experienced a reduced risk of
developing adenomomas even six years
later. So because of that, we have to
give bourbon a perfect A score for the
effectiveness score card. However,
because we're basing this on a single
randomized control trial, which is an
excellent source of evidence, it's
nonetheless a single study with a
follow-up based on the same data. So,
until we get more evidence from other
labs or just more studies in general,
let's cool it on the strength of
evidence score and give it a C. The dose
used was 600 mg per day. Curcumin for
arthritis.
Ah, yes, the golden spice. This one was
a mixture of clinical evidence in humans
and mechanistic evidence in animals.
Essentially, both forms of evidence
indicated that curcumin has a mild pain
relief and joint function improving
effect. Now, I wouldn't consider this
the I don't know the elixir of a
painfree life or anything, but it has a
noticeable impact. Of course, personal
mileage will vary since we're discussing
averages. Now, I'd rate the strength of
evidence quite high, a B, and I'm even
tempted to say an A simply because
there's not just one or two studies, but
over 30 studies on the topic, granted of
varying quality. Now, on the other hand,
the effect size is mild. So, I will put
the score for effectiveness at a C. The
dose used for standard curcumin was
1,000 to 2,000 milligrams per day.
There's also other forms of curcumin
that I discuss in my extended analysis
exclusive for the physionic insiders
research review which is linked in the
description. Uralithna and immune aging.
Now I covered this over a year ago once
and then I covered it again I maybe
about a month ago or so because a new
study had published on this molecule
called uriththna. It's touted as a
molecule that relieves pain like in arth
osteoarthritis. It's a mphagy activator.
It improves exercise performance and
most recently it combats the immune
system decline as we get older. So in
older individuals. So it sounds pretty
impressive considering the scope is so
wide. And there's multiple randomized
control trials to back up some of these
claims. However, the reality is far more
bleak as I explained in my videos. But
the bottom line is that the words are
more impressive than the data indicates.
Usually the studies don't focus on
functional outcomes like actual
improvements in joint function for
example and tend to focus too much in my
opinion on molecular mechanisms. Then
the few times that function is assessed
the effect is small. So, the strength of
evidence I'll give it a B simply because
there are several human trials. However,
the effect size I'll give a D. Typical
dose is 1,000 milligs per day. Omega-3
fats and dementia. Now, I covered
omega-3 fats and their impact on our
brain a long time ago. Now, covering, I
don't know, like 10 or more studies,
many eons ago, my boy. But a new
metaanalysis released going into more
depth in relation to dementia
prevention. Now, it ultimately concurred
with multiple other trials that omega-3s
are important for reducing the risk of
dementia, a generalized term for uh
brain disorders. They also did some
unique things in that analysis,
including doing a small prospective
study. But ultimately, what you want to
know is if it works or not, and the
answer is yes. The strength of evidence
is good, though it could still use a
little bit of work. And we can give it,
let's say, a B, leaning towards an A.
Again, also, the effect size is a tricky
one because the immediate effect is
quite small, but the long-term benefit
could be quite sizable based on the
evidence that we have. So, I'd give it a
B. Doses can vary, and even low doses
like 500 milligrams can make a
meaningful difference. Though the
greatest bang for your buck, remember
that it is for the brain, not for the
heart, is one gram of omega-3s. Lithium
and Alzheimer's disease. So, staying in
the puzzling world of cognition, a
player that is finally achieving
recognition is elemental lithium. There
was a major study released this last
year, but the reality is there have been
multiple human trials using lithium as
well. So, it's not exactly new, just
kind of new to the spotlight.
Ultimately, we have evidence that
elemental lithium can play a role
against Alzheimer's disease, helping
stave off the disease. I wouldn't go as
far as to say that you we don't need any
more evidence. I'd like to see more, but
we do have some solid evidence from
multiple human studies as well as this
new major nature paper. So, let's say
the evidence is a B. Now, the strength
of the effect, the effect size is quite
substantial if you think of the
long-term implications. I don't want you
to think that lithium is going to cure
Alzheimer's or anything, but it seems to
have a pretty sizable impact. So, let's
say the effect size is rated at a B,
being conservative. The dose used in
trials of elemental lithium is 400
micrograms. Collagen for skin. I've
covered this before, but there was a big
meta analysis that scared a few people
off the collagen fork skin bandwagon.
However, I and several others stood
broad swords and hands staring the
villainous dragon in the eye and
defended their beloved collagen because
it turned out that the meta analysis was
properly misunderstood. And when looking
at the studies independently, the vast
majority reported benefits of collagen
supplementation for skin. Anyway,
there's plenty of bad studies in the
collagen world. I've analyzed at least
12, and I still wouldn't be shocked if
better evidence subdued our excitement
some. However, so far, the strength of
evidence is in the C range. A lot of
studies, but only a few are of higher
quality. The effect size is also decent,
but not earthshattering. So, let's say
it's also a C. The dose used in trials
varies, but usually it's around 10 gram
of hydrayzeed collagen. Mangaperin for
the brain. This is a molecule that comes
out of the mango. Funny enough, I think
I I think I mispronounced it in every
single time in my dedicated video on the
topic. Still, it's a molecule that's
believed to reduce inflammation in the
brain, which leads to improved brain
function. Or at least that's the idea.
Unfortunately, most of the evidence is
mechanistic and what human studies do
exist are very short in duration. That
means that for the strength of evidence,
we'd have to give it a D. And for effect
size, I'm afraid it's also going to
disappoint the parents over the break
until next semester, another D. If
you're still inclined, the extracts of
mangaperin are consumed at around 400
milligrams per day. Collagen for joints.
Let us get into the joint, not the
smoking kind, the kind that allows you
to move around. And let's return to
collagen. Now, for this one, I expected
a bit more, but honestly, the effects
were mild, though admittedly widespread.
The unfortunate part is that most
studies are in people who have serious
joint ailments like arthritis. And if
the effect is mild for them, what are
the odds that we'll get much if we don't
have major joint pain or function
issues? I'd guess slim at best, but
that's just speculation. So, the
strength of evidence, not bad. Probably
like a C, maybe a B simply because there
are plenty of studies, but they're not
all the greatest quality. And for
effectiveness, we can keep it at a C as
well. Keep in mind that likely gets
devalued to a D or even an F if you
don't have joint issues, you're young,
and so on. It may increase if you're
older and compound that with some form
of arthritis. The dose used is typically
at the skin dose of 10 grams per day or
greater. Let's discuss magnesium for the
brain. If you're wondering what are
reputable sources for all these
supplements and it'd be nice to have one
place where everything is put together
for you by dosing, disease, effect size,
source across all supplements analyzed,
not just these 15. Then check out my
master supplement list. It just launched
and will be updated regularly exclusive
for the physionic insiders. There's also
a new AI that I built that has been
educated on all my analyses to date. So,
you can ask your questions that get
answers based on my work. Oh, and of
course, you get all these perks right
over here, like a private monthly
podcast, articles that go with every
video, live sessions with me, and much
more. I put a ton of work into the
insiders because it's a way that I can
keep myself independent and offer
quality work devoid of sponsor influence
or perceived influence. Anyway, check it
out by using the link in the
description. Oh, right. Magnesium.
So, this was focused on the health of
the brain and the relationship to
magnesium. Honestly, the evidence is
quite convoluted. There's little
evidence in favor of supplementation as
it relates to the brain. And there's
even studies indicating excess magnesium
can carry risk. So, what to do? Just aim
for the recommended dietary allowance.
That's around 400 milligrams per day for
men. and 320 milligrams for women. The
strength of evidence is weak. I'd give
it a D. And the effectiveness is so
convoluted at present. I would give it
an F. As I'm sure some people will
ignore the previous warnings. It always
happens. I am not saying that magnesium
is not good for your general health. I
am saying that the evidence for brain
health and magnesium supplementation
specifically is very weak. One thing
that is often overlooked when discussing
blood pressure and heart health is the
inclusion of a particular electrolyte,
potassium and heart disease. So, sodium
is often the target for reducing blood
pressure. But did you know that
potassium, its sibling atom, is also a
potent regulator of blood pressure?
Well, in studies looking at potassium
intake, there's good evidence that
focusing on potassium intake can not
only reduce blood pressure, but
meaningfully reduce stroke risk. On the
strength of evidence, we're talking
about a solid B. And in terms of
effectiveness, we're talking an A. This
can really help a lot of people dealing
with elevated blood pressure. Now,
dosing is tricky because potassium can
be also quite dangerous if it's over
consumed. Generally, just keeping it in
balance with sodium intake is a good
overall step. Otherwise, if you use salt
on your food, consider switching it out
for a 25% potassium chloride salt. The
taste is very similar, but the added
potassium in place of sodium leads to
improved cardiovascular health alone.
Mediumchain triglycerides and arthritis.
There's a trial that I covered looking
at the impact MCTs or mediumchain
triglycerides might have at improving
symptoms of rheumatoid arthritis. Now,
ultimately the study showed some
benefit, but if you looked at the study
a bit closer, there was bias therein
which I'll leave for my full analysis
which is linked if you're interested.
Now ultimately we have one human study
that indicates effectiveness of MCTs on
rheumatoid arthritis. And considering
some of the limitations of that study,
I'd put the strength of evidence at a D,
while I'd put the effect size at a D as
well. I think there's a possibility for
that to change as more research emerges,
but this evidence didn't leave much for
positive impression, though it does lean
in the direction of MCTs working. The
dose used, FYI, was 30 grams per day.
The next one might catch me some flak,
but let's discuss methylene blue and
cognitive health. Now, there are
randomized control trials, but they are
few and far between. Yet, there are some
scientific reviews that if you read them
make compelling case for methylene blues
potential. Unfortunately, that's the key
word there, potential, because the
studies are pretty poor quality with
metal methodological issues or looking
at inconsequential outcomes like blood
flow to the brain. What other studies
exist are mechanistic nature and there
are some studies on dementia in humans,
but the results are kind of all over the
place. So, as much as some people swear
by methylene blue, the strength of
evidence is a D and the effect size is
also a D until we can get more
convincing data on the brain effects. I
have reviewed the longevity and aging
effects before as well, and I'll link
that review for you. Keep in mind that
just because we don't have good quality
studies on something doesn't mean that
it doesn't work. But what it does mean
is that by the strict scientific lens,
we can't fudge the truth and say that
there's strong scientific basis for a
supplement. Doing is really all over the
place, too. So, for this one, I'm going
to skip it. I'll combine these two
simply because they're both related to
muscle mass. HMBB or beta hydroxy beta
methylbutyrate, quite a mouthful, and
TMG or trimethyl glycine are two
compounds that have been studied in
several human trials. In total, both of
these do just about nothing if they
aren't paired with exercise, especially
resistance training. However, assuming
that you do train, both of these have
modest benefits increasing muscle mass.
The quality of evidence is fair and
since there are quite a few studies, I'd
say that the strength of evidence is at
least deserving of a C. However, the
effect size is small. So, if you don't
train, well, the effect size is an F.
And if you do train, it's a C. Both are
kind of middle of the road. Now, I
realize that you may be taking TMG, also
known as betane, to reduce homocyine
levels. That's a conversation for
another time, though. dosing is around
2.5 to three grams for either. Now,
let's get into the final one. Vitamin D
and bone health. This one was a
surprising one because it had some
counterintuitive results. For example,
vitamin D supplementation was beneficial
for preserving bone in people who are
vitamin D deficient. However, very high
doses in the tens and even hundreds of
thousands of IUs, that's international
units, there's a signal that vitamin D
actually worsens bone health. So dose
matters. Low doses less than a thousand
IUs was shown to be beneficial for those
with vitamin D deficiency. There's
pretty good evidence for all this. So
I'll rate it a B on the quality of
evidence. However, the effectiveness is
tightly tied to a person's vitamin D
status. If they have normal levels,
supplementation for bone health has
minimal impact. Maybe placing it at a D
and not for vitamin D, but because it's
just not that great. On the other hand,
for people with vitamin D deficiency, as
defined by regular blood panel values,
vitamin D climbs up to a C. It still
doesn't have massive effects. They
remain pretty modest, but that could
also be because bone mineralization
takes years, and the studies don't all
last that long, yielding an effect,
though more modest. Now, I'll repeat
this again, too. Blood values will be
increased for the majority of people
with a modest dosing. So, some people
may need more. And we are again talking
about averages. I would be cautious
about over consuming though as
mentioned. Okay, here we are. We've
summarized a lot and I have hours and
hours of me discussing all these topics
in dedicated analyses that I sh burden
you with now, but you're welcome to
check them out in the description.
However, what are the supplements that I
recommend if I had to limit it to just a
few? This is based on this year's worth
of analysis, but also last year's
analysis.
Nothing has changed from my votes of
last year. I have a short list of
creatine, omega-3s, the combination of
luteine and zeazanthin, and that's it.
Creatine affects the brain. It affects
the musculature. Omega-3s impact the
brain and the cardiovascular system. And
lutein and zeazanthin have excellent
evidence for eye health. The choices
change based on individual circumstance,
but if you don't have specific issues
that you want help dealing with and you
just want to support your general
health, those are great choices. This,
of course, assumes that you're taking
care of your overall nutrition,
exercising, sleeping to the best of your
ability, supplements will never overcome
missing out on those three. But if
you're looking for other supplements
with evidence behind them for different
outcomes because you just can't help but
buy more supplements, then check out my
last summary right over here. I hope
this helped. Thanks for tuning in. I'll
catch you in the next one. See you.